[Music]
Friday at 11 at 1:00 1:30 or something
my my son was born hmm yeah Gabrielle
Gabrielle Adam Sweeney biblical names
biblical names even got you know an Arch
Angel this time exactly yeah
like I like you've been inspired by our
conversations about the Messiah haven't
you probably probably but anything
anything big buckle I'm into that
mm-hmm that's very you know a biblical
Buddhist yeah we can't really locate
ourselves within Christianity to begin
with it's part of our history a heritage
but we're not Christians any longer so
we have to go somewhere else to find
inspiration and for me that has been the
Silk Route try it that's been the study
of Zoroastrianism Taoism and Buddhism
and I find the whole worldview that
appears they're totally superior to
begin with because it's monist and
secondly because it's also much wiser
it's much older so there's much more to
get from it mm-hmm yeah so the early
Christianity is defined by its lacks
it's the it's it's defined by what it
lacks and of course interesting enough
when we get to the 19th century and you
know the great Germans like Hegel and
Nietzsche they all they all deal with
negation or lack and I think that's a
you know typical Protestant reaction to
the inherent locks to Christianity to
begin with as opposed to plenitude and
and fullness and whoa we arrived at the
20th century arrive at the cost we had
for separating Church of state in the
West and as John said the case that I've
argued all along everything is religion
and if you try to pretend you do do
something outside of religion you're
really dangerous territory that's what
you end up with colonialism and Hitler
and Stalin which are of course the
Heritage's of the west and we
misunderstood that as you know a failure
of patriarchy when in reality it's a
patchwork II that is not dictated the
way a patriarchy should be which is it
should be part of a religion or it
should be its own religion to be honest
about so we left in math
turkey as a religion which is
Christianity and we left with Patrick a
they were been celebrating a separate
from religion as science and politics
for example and that's exactly why
things have gone wrong hmm okay well we
were today we were gonna talk about the
dialogue between David Chapman and genre
Vicki in regards to the film the Joker
yeah which I reacted to it and wrote
wrote a couple blog blogs on and I think
it relates to what you're saying and I
was thinking this morning about about
the Joker figure and I was thinking
about his comparing him to let's say the
the figure of Satan and in Dante and the
figure of Satan and Dante is is kind of
a caricature right he's he's kind of a
he's kind of a letdown right he's this
monstrous figure and and and my insight
was that this Joker character is there's
there's a kind of realism in him right
he's he's being he's being humanized and
made more real and he has a backstory
and I don't know if you've seen the film
yet have you
I haven't been I know it really well
anyway the the film's a little different
than the previous Joker films because
there's no supernatural element to it
right he's just he's just a guy and also
it's different because there's no
superheroes like there's no there's no
Batman and it's just about him right
it's very clear it's human and he's the
ultimate narcissist and the ultimate
tragedy and he has this sort of you know
he's as mental illness and all that kind
of thing and so the Joker
so I was thinking the Joker is alone as
the Satan figure without any grand
narratives without without a superhero
you know I think you're missing an
important point with this specific but
it's called Joker not on the Joker and
there's a reason
yeah so we can person if I am identified
with him he's a very modern modern guy
he's not the Joker and exactly so so the
whole the whole process of him coming
out of the supernatural is what I've
been thinking about and and the sort of
end of end of end of grand narratives
and end of end of post and the beginning
of post-modernism and so he's just
figure as you say without without any
religion except for chief
entertainment and he lives with his
mother he's sort of a Jordan Peter
Sounion kind of loser like the guy who
never leaves home and and so anyway I
thought the film was really interesting
for its sort of inversion of all of the
the typical Hollywood you know the
typical Joker myths right and also this
good versus evil duality which is so
strong in in most of you know the good
guy always wins but in this in this in
this film it's just this sort of bare
realism and then and then he has this
kind of New Age enlightenment almost
right he becomes he becomes like
enlightened in the negative sense it
becomes an egomaniac and the Buddhist
tradition they called Rudra he sort of
he realizes that he has nothing to lose
and and he can do anything he wants and
he becomes completely amoral and then he
becomes a sort of terrorist right so
it's excellent material so the number
one thing here please observe that the
assumption that the movie is based on
its the fact that this guy is somebody
who's left religion behind and that's
some kind of advancement or or necessary
so our basic arguments at so the
christen are using in our work is that
the lack of religion is what's causing
this and there's no reason why there
should be a lack of religion in the
first place mmm-hmm we're basically
accusing all the modern atheists or just
lacking imagination right that's why
synth ISM is called crepe in God in the
Internet age we seriously mean exactly
that so if you want to have a god you
need to create a God there you create
the God that's what people have always
done
that's how religion is formulated and
religion is then it contained there
within which you can add so you need a
match Oracle religion or magical
religion you need a masculine religion
or what you call a phallic religion you
need you need an understanding of math
turkey and patriarchy to begin with
- then contain the - within a normandy
ology so no modalities the word we're
using for an religion for the container
for religion itself so we're interested
in religion as religion we don't talk
about in Pacific religion here we talk
about religion and its function in
society this is why we have this saying
everything is religion and if you
tendus anything else then you end up
with stupid religions like Nazism and
Stalinism in capitalism okay
give us a good definition of religion
then religion is what connects people to
one another's as soon as there is some
kind of communication between two or
more human beings that has to happen
within a religious container that means
for example the individualism is a
religion yeah believe in capitalism not
the practice with the belief in
capitalism is a religion and and so is
also socialism and liberalism
there are also religions they're
different religious expressions they
have to be understood as such as usually
as bad religion because they don't work
so you have to go back and read the
formal religions are and this is where
we go back to the origin of the West the
separation of Europe and the Middle East
which is very important here and that
starts in the fifth century and that
leads to Islam dominating the Middle
East and Christianity dominating the
world the West but they're both Gnostic
religions and the problem with
Gnosticism is that because it's separate
spirit and body he starts separating
everything and the way we've taken on
Gnosticism in the West and celebrated it
is by claiming that it was success for
us to separate church and state I think
that was the big mistake mm-hmm okay and
that is a typically Christian phenomenon
and why that happened was that in the
5th century we separate the two dominant
modes in the Roman Empire when they fell
apart they were called Christianity
Mithraism
in Mithraism was the military religion
so it's the religion that was phallic
and Christianity served really well it's
the religion that celebrated the mother
of the child the celebration of the
mother and the child is fundamental
because it is our future
you just had a son you had your your
your woman gave birth to your son
so she's the mother of your son the fact
that that happened means that there's a
future you have your future path I don't
have any biological children at least
not officially so I don't have that path
I can only share your path but I support
your path but I don't have that path
because I don't know children so the
idea of mother and children being a
religion in itself is absolutely
fundamental it's the fundamental
religion Buddhism and Christianity have
those traits but you need to complement
that Buddhism found that eventually at a
very high cost
Christianity still hasn't you need to
complement that with the phallic
religion this is why we call Jordan
Peterson surge towards reintroducing
religion into our thinking we call that
phallic and therefore we call him his or
aster
so this is the phallic mission that the
West desperately needs mm-hmm we needed
we needed phallic religion again so that
we can contain things like politics and
the military and all those things within
the religious container okay so let's
can I go back to the Joker film a little
bit and you got describe eyes he's a
young guy and he's kind of you know he
still have says with his mother you know
he hasn't learned how to live in the
sense he hasn't yet yes there's no
structure around him not you know for
him to develop into into something you
know he could have been an artist in a
way he sort of the failed al Adolphe
Hitler right he he's the artist who you
know who fails and remains kind of as
you say that the boy the boy he becomes
a boy King in a way yeah
Joker he's a man he's a woman he's a
young man
he's also an atheist clearly he's post
religious post Christian and even the
script of the movie assumes that that's
a position he has to have yeah
interesting okay so the predicament here
I said he actually built into the
assumptions of the script itself mm-hmm
this is what he said guy who's lost his
religion he's the guy who was like the
REM so I'm losing my religion like
that's the result of that whole you know
I know you dopey I don't know what it
was but that whole nihilism or that
whole sort of I guess you would say I
don't know whatever it was that started
in the 1960s where you didn't need a sex
and you didn't need a religion and you
didn't need a you know an institution
and you know you just want to be
yourself it's kind of a American
individualism and that is very much a
religion okay we're all alone we're all
fighting each other especially men and
we all have established some kind of ego
and then one day we die okay that's
American individualism so that's why the
American individual
to prolong his life as much as possible
and that's why the American
individualist especially in Silicon
Valley today are the guys who talk the
most about living forever now anybody
who talks about living forever does so
because he doesn't have a life here and
now mm-hmm no one the reason why you'd
be interested in living forever is
because you postpone your life you don't
live it now you can't live your life if
you're only ideal religion is the
religion is something for children and
women mm-hmm which is essentially the
post Christian Western assumption today
that's interesting in the film the guy
is only interested in his mother and in
kids he's only interested in mother and
children right exactly his mother and
and he takes care of his mother and he
wants to make children smile and his
whole raison d'etre is that basically
women and children then it doesn't seem
like there's there's a there's a there's
any the only male role model he has is a
kind of median on TV or something and so
exactly so you if you only have
Christianity or possibly Buddhism as the
alternatives you're still in the arm of
the religion of mother and child so like
that would be the only religion that's
exactly what Joker ends up with some
kind of New Age enlightenment where he
has a man can only do one thing and that
is to plunder the world that is
precisely my point if you look at the
history of the West the last 1600s after
Christianity became our only official
religion in the West and we got rid of
the military religion and we left the
phallic energy you know the energy of
wanting to get higher and improve on
something and make it better we left
that to this state so we left it to the
military and we left it to the new arena
called politics that's we put all the
men this is what feminism is wrongly
accused of being patriarchy no it is a
misdirected patriarchy we have to patch
our key and we have to matter ok we've
always argued in our work that you need
both ok but the pack turkeys misdirected
so what would men do if they do not have
a religion that contained their phallic
energy that applies wisdom to the
phallic energy it just operates on what
favourtie calls the level of
intelligence but without rationality
mmm-hmm it would become Joker right they
would even become what the West became
it would become a system like colonizes
and then plunders the world mm-hmm it
becomes a state a permanent exploitation
yeah except the Joker as the Joker's
late capitalism in it comes at the end
of all that right he's the late
capitalist yeah doctor we're all there's
left is entertainment and what you would
call more Tito or you know yes driver
for for narcissistic drive for pleasure
and destruction or something like that
I don't know what yeah it's a kind of
vulgar Nietzschean ism in this in the
shape you've seen it of the past 30 or
40 years so late last year and other
thinkers have gone into the cynical mood
saying that there's no hope for us we're
left with this religion called
individualism we're left with the cart
and there's nothing beyond that and we
can even critique Nietzsche for never
understanding that aristocrat that he
celebrates the ubermensch has to be some
kind of a collective that's why I'm
bringing Marx back into the picture okay
through Marx proletariat that we
actually have a client or a tribe all
men who can operate together and that's
what religion should have done so if you
bring religion to Nietzsche's philosophy
you will start getting things right we
have to understand the phallic energy as
something that needs to be controlled
and contained within a religion phallic
religion is a response to that okay so
in yeah you talked about Marx last time
and also Nietzsche and you also talked
about them being heroic so yeah the
other thought I then thought I had is
that the Joker is sort of the absence of
the heroic heroic that's any sense yeah
and and again we have this discussion
about how how everybody's very reluctant
to to go into the heroic because they're
afraid of totalitarianism and all that
but we want we want he want to bring
back the heroic in some sense so in what
sense well the alternative to the heroic
is Joker the whole time to the rock is a
cynical manipulator and exploiter what
else would it be
if you take a young man and you put him
forward toward in front of the elderly
what would they do with him they put him
through the initiation ritual to knock
his ego out and then make him serve the
communities his life can become
meaningless this is the shift from me
from me Chinese into Marxism in a good
way that that means you need to serve
your community and if you don't find a
role you serve the community you're lost
Joker has those it's ro why because
religion is the one thing that supplies
the role within that community so the
the ultimate religious ritual is the
initiation ritual of the young man and
because he didn't acknowledges that he's
there to serve the community and because
if he serves the community he doesn't
serve his own ego he gets out of his
imprisonment and he can then be set free
to serve the community which is the
purpose of the Falak religion this is
called transcendence yeah it's so
interesting yeah because in the film I
just let me just in the film he he has
this this is a spoiler but he has this
he funds he's not his mother is not
really his mother and let's say his
father figure is not really his father
and he kills them both right so he kills
the mother and the father so he kills
both the matriarch and the patriarchy in
a certain sense but he kills them
because they failed to be match our kin
patriarch because they don't have a
religion within which they can act the
roles attract in a metric yeah the thing
he kills in he has fake name a jerk in
the fake patriarchy and so he's just
enacting the the dis archetype when when
it's not working or when when the whole
thing isn't working well he has he has
inherited the worldview from them and
the world is inherited is that life is
certainly meaningless Joker is born into
a world without religion
a world without religion for men at
least the only remnant of religion
that's left is the religion - celebrates
mother and child so his own upbringing
he said he leaves religion because it's
tight his childhood and as soon as it
becomes an adult is thrown into a world
where ironically the only religion that
exists American individualism in
American individualism has preached for
the past three or four hundred years
that you you're on your own
all you can do is to try to colonize and
exploit the world
possibly can well that was like you know
Bret Easton Ellis in the 1980s to begin
with so this is just like the follow-up
of that this is like the mass version of
America but I didn't I didn't get the
American Psycho oh yeah Britney's not
sure exactly Joker Joker is the
repetition of the tragedy of American
Psycho as farce
that's essentially what Joker's so
arrived that American psyche has become
a mass phenomenon away
no there's nothing stopping you from
doing that this is why we introduced the
term employ tation in a work because you
take the word exploitation when you
tweak it and you turn it around you turn
around simply because it is a different
attitude to the assets you have in front
of you so when we talk about for example
a circular economy and we kind of
plunder the planet any longer what's on
environmentalism is open the door to
that we now to move into a katoki anism
which is again is turning
environmentalism into a proper religion
into proper wisdom
so a koto pianist would then say okay
because you can exploit something you
would just you know burn the candle in
one end and then you'll destroy yourself
and you'll destroy the future and you
will not have children so exploitation
has to end you have to have an attitude
towards the world which is employed with
it the trick we're doing in the new work
we're working with now is that we then
define the universe in contemporary
society and the hubris is all these
dozen boys running around saying we must
explore space much conquer space
well conquering space is the nothing but
the idea that we can repeat the mistakes
of the past we can stay outside of
religion or pretend that individualism
is not a religion so that we can exploit
and plunder other planets instead of
plundering this one because this one is
finished would it be better to just
realize that it's incredibly difficult
and incredibly costly and for human body
absolutely possible to live in outer
space outer space to miss the Tower of
Babel of today so you need to return
through the planet earth itself explain
explain outer space is the Tower of
Babel because that's an interesting
statement right it means that there's
nothing for us to find on Mars and
nothing for us to
I mean it's just endless expansion into
into you know into nothingness sir there
is nowhere to go and he's incredibly
expensive and it's just cold and there's
nothing there no you know the moon
landing was a disaster we haven't even
returned what was the moon a damn rock
full of radiation and cold like hell why
didn't you go used to Siberia because
nobody's left in Siberia territory
something we have abundance of territory
and you said that before telling us
Ellen must should go to Siberia right
instead of instead of Mars it is warmer
it is closer far less expensive and
there's nobody there well all those
resources yeah I mean obviously we
should direct them on to it to our own
planet it seems ok so this is what
implication tells you implication to us
you got a resource in front of you not
why don't you use it in a way that you
actually replace it as soon as you use
it so we do that for example with water
we have to do with energy we have to do
with anything that is a flow of any kind
in our society to create the Bundys
that's needed this turns out to be a
perfect project for a phallic energy
mm-hmm right okay so all the engineers
of the world need to be united the
engineers of the world have to define
themselves as the proper Marxist
proletariat they need to take over the
world
and they need to do it with an
employment of spirit which is that we're
gonna stay on this planet we're gonna
cultivate all of this planet and we're
going to essentially create a Garden of
Babel instead of a Tower of Babel that's
gonna be planet Earth well this planet
Earth we can then live on this is the
idea of appropriate the garden of gobble
the garden about and this is what the
engineer's the future Chief James would
do the future priests who then have
commercial itself and something we call
cosmopolitanism which is to build the
machine intelligence that helps people
to love the stranger you see how utopian
these visions are they're all built on
the idea that we couldn't spark or
religion that works and if you construct
the phallic religion that works then we
can pretty much leave the market
religion to Buddhism Christianity a new
age whatever you want to do with it
we have those religions already we can
save them in that sense the
cuz there's something that complements
them so my response too young for
Varrick is that he's absolutely right
about everything in his Buddhism but
he's only half before mm-hmm as a Joan
of Arc is not getting a large following
a young men who are like oh wow
young for Varrick is the shape we're
gonna follow him Jordan Peters and did
and we increasingly are too so if you
speak directly to men about phallic
energy you need for a fire collision in
our society you there like our picture
yes of course which is meaningful and
it's meaningful because it is a religion
okay
cynical atheistic exercise okay okay
I'm a bit stuck on this thing everything
is religion because you could if you you
could almost say anything you know like
if everything is a religion then nothing
is a religion isn't isn't it a no didn't
say that I said everything is so little
buddy see they're a good religion or a
bad religion a bad religion is one that
doesn't recognize that it is a religion
because because I was I was oh he
doesn't recognize that is a religion so
perhaps the jokerz world is that he is
kind of following a religion but it's
just a negative religion he's father
than individualism he's following
American individualism he's the ultimate
American individual ultimately where you
arrive if you're an America - pretends
you don't have a religion well you are
your own religion your own fucking big
Eagle religion okay but you see but
there's let's say there's a formal can
we say there's a formal religion and in
formal religion like your Zoroastrians I
and and and I'm a Buddhist and that's a
formal religion and then all the other
things that we are are just sort of sub
religions or informal know you're down
the wrong path that's not interesting at
all former religion formalization of
religion is only something that an
organization like a state makes out of
religion later in history when you use
the word Buddhism for example you're
applying a 19th century European fairy
tale innovation on the schools of
thought in the east that were never
described as Buddhist schools they were
they're supposed to be schools and we're
yeah
schools so religion the reason why you
don't have a separation or religion of
the secular in the East is because all
the three dominant modes were talking
about
so rastan ism Taoism and Buddhism armed
honest now if you if you're am honest if
you believe that everything in the world
is related to everything else you cannot
have anything outside of religion okay
so you met with David Chapman about
monism because he's very um he considers
monism to be the sort of New Age he
think he thinks monism so you say
everything is one right everything is
one substance and therefore you make no
distinction and something wrong you
assumed that therefore you cannot
differentiate that is stupid okay
everything is one but it has many many
everyone it doesn't mean Spinoza said
it's formatively we have to go back to
school nonsense i also said there is
only one substance and everything is
within that substance but within that
substance there's an infinite amount of
attributes mm-hmm okay multiplicity
always exists to the you know it's like
birdsong said and rebug song said why is
there so much of everything and he said
that as a leading Western modest no so
this one so I guess you guys have a
different version of monism because the
critique of monism that I've heard would
be that it's you can't say things are
one and you can't say things are many
it's non-dualism there's there's not one
knows how he talks about things he
doesn't know about that just love me and
their mana modernism is is a substantial
ization of things it makes the world
into something it's reifies you know the
world into something whereas we can't
really say it's something and anyway
I've just heard these arguments and
Buddhist circles a lot so I'm just
throwing them out there with well
they're stupid what you mean so why
would there be dualism to begin with why
would they be even too
separate substances that have no
connection one another well it will need
the cock in the 16 parties what's every
idea dualism of secular dualism
inherited from Christianity nanotech
part all along the spiritual body was
separate God from the Gnostics this is
all Augustine this is all Manichaean ISM
I know it because it's starting in Iran
it's a separation of Ahriman and
enormous though so the separation of the
pill so you but when I finish it so so
you right at the the secular agnosticism
but for America is today so you
separated church and state you separated
spiritual body you say these are
different substances but the question
because already from his own students
was but if these are two different
substances how do they communicate with
each other through which third necessary
substance do they communicate so you end
up with split after split after split
after split mmm until you finally
realize because if two different
substances are communicating with one
another they're really one substance
this is what monism teaches mmm only
simple gravity teaches us that gravity
everything affects everything else in
the universe you can't say there's
anything outside of the University kids
and anything separate from it so monism
is radical and it's true it's
non-negotiable
you don't have any arguments against it
but then the question is why the hell
this is for various problem why the hell
do people want to be Gnostics beginning
why do they want to be doing this and I
think for work it right and arrives at
this question naively he says that
because they want to be something higher
or more normal than what they are my
response phase they know they just
little petty bourgeois snobs who want to
look little superior to their neighbor I
find Gnostics to be absolutely human and
very very small minded very
narrow-minded and they're obsessed with
activating finality oh why you see like
Gnosticism it's also the origin of
Russell mm-hmm so if if you're gonna
make it clean split with that okay I get
all that I get all that I'm just I'm
trying to figure out like why why insist
on you know
in the circles that I've you know they
assist on non-dualism rather than saying
monism because they are ignorant
hey did haven't even studied philosophy
if you study philosophy
a lot of Americans read two books I
think your fucking neck what more can I
say
if you've started the history of
philosophy you know to begin with dosa
you know some eight inches there's no
valid critiques of of monism or anywhere
and in philosophy
no more nism one big time with Hegel and
Nietzsche ninety century eventually no
saponin to the cart anemometer LeConte
makes the last attempt at trying to
separate the few substances of the carts
universe and I would say so the
breakdown of the cart starts with his
completion this is often the case in
philosophy when somebody thinks and I D
all the way through and Kant is the
realization of the cart so counties
where arrived with individualism and the
current crisis and can't can't get out
of it
so he's accomplished that but of course
an after Immanuel Kant Spinoza comes on
yeah you know so and it also went
through Hegel Spinoza ways through
Nietzsche and of course you get guys
like Freud and Jung they're impossible
without confers and we see the
compliment and it's see that it's
impossible to overcome
now you either deal with that by saying
but either you have to live with a smoke
or you can overcome the split my
responsibility we can definitely
overcome this with as long as we
understood pack a bit family american
separate we have to live in a universe
of two religions hmm celebrating same
universe okay we can even have four
that's what the citizen book claims
that's a different story
it has to do with the fact that our
drive system is split into four and our
way of understanding the worlds of the
way we approach knowledge it's also
split into four what at least we can
split them within this same damn
universe so we're saying that women and
men are not opposed to each other they
have to collaborate and actually to be
human is to understand what is a man
woman you're only one-half that is
precisely what - and breaches but if you
look at Megan saying why do we have
these two turns money summit non-dualism
know do we listen it's just cheating
it's just none what is it then so my
response to people insist on the term
non-dualism is that why do you want to
keep the word dualism in the first place
just acknowledge the fact we have a
modest world view if or anything seem to
connect with everything else you have to
understand the world monastic Lee so but
if you accept your immodest you cannot
have anything outside a religion because
if you have it outside a religion he
will not be religious any longer he will
be profane and you will exploit it and
you use it and you will kill it that's
exactly what we have done in the West we
can call that a lack of wisdom if you
like you can call like a lack of sense
of history we can certainly call it a
lack of knowledge but at the end of the
day it is like a plundering energy pure
drive mechanistic pure drive without I
thought this container of let's say of
the tribe or of the Sochi on Thai think
you call it understanding
I thought only sort of wisdom of wisdom
can you maybe you could talk about
wisdom what you mean by was that okay
it's also lack of context or Aristotle
is important here it's not only the
tribe or only this also of course not
because that becomes of plundering
insults young that's not much better so
that's essentially what a colonial izing
nation-state from Europe does without
the continent the constructs right so no
you have to see the context and the
context has to be approached with an
employee to t'v attitude exploitation
when we tame the urge to exploit and and
in you go through the association ritual
and you start to serve the community and
by serving the community y'alls assert
that serve the surrounding world yeah so
that's what we have to do with machines
so increasing this well the way we've
done it before with materials with
plants and with animals we're going to
have the same attitude how do we
domesticate the machine for that equal
parents
okay that's the next big issue so that's
that that's the next issue with you know
so-called AI or whatever is that is how
to domesticate the machine you see you
say so how do we do but I'm terrified if
American secular individualist are gonna
be the guys to run the machine we're
gonna hawk we're gonna cause enormous
havoc we're not absolutely absolutely so
you know we trust these guys with the
nuclear bomb you know to begin with I
don't want to trust them with the
machine do we so we need to step back a
bit